Guide to the Schieffelin Family Papers
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Schieffelin family papers
1779-1992
WA MSS S-1401
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
4.75
(9 boxes)
The papers document the Jacob Schieffelin family of New York and Pennsylvania, and their involvment with land development and real estate in Tioga and Lycoming counties, Pennsylvania, mining in the West, and the founding of Tombstone, Arizona. The papers of Clinton Schieffelin contain information on mining in California and Oregon as well as in Indian affairs in the Rogue River Valley. Edward L. Schieffelin's papers describe silver mining in Arizona, and gold prospecting in Alaska. The collection contains two diaries of Denison A. Lockwood, a friend of the family from Tioga, Pennsylvania. His diaries describe an 1849 voyage on the ship Morrison which he, Jacob, and Jacob's sons, Edward and Alfred, took to California via Cape Horn.
Schieffelin, Jacob, 1793-1880
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Donated by Mary Schieffelin Brady, 1977.
Conditions Governing Access
The originals in Box 6, folders 94, 96 are owned by the Bancroft Library, University of California, Berkeley. No reproduction permitted. Contact the Bancroft Library if photocopy is desired.
THE SCHIEFFELIN FAMILY
Jacob Schieffelin, Sr., born in 1757, joined the loyalist army and served as Henry Hamilton's secretary during the Revolutionary War. He was captured in 1779 and held prisoner in Williamsburg, Virginia. Schieffelin escaped to Canada, where in 1780 he was appointed lieutenant in the Queen's Rangers by Henry Clinton. He spent time in Montreal and Detroit but returned to New York and founded a drug company with his brother Lawrence in 1794.
Jacob's company bought, sold, and imported drugs, medicines, fancy goods, perfumes, and other merchandise. In 1813, the business passed to Jacob's sons, Henry, Effingham, and Jacob, Jr., who renamed it H. H. Schieffelin & Co. In 1848, the name changed to Schieffelin Brothers & Co., which dissolved in 1865 and became W. H. Schieffelin & Co., with many of the same partners. Retaining its name, the partnership reformed again in 1870, with primarily the same people. By 1879 the firm had disappeared.
Jacob and his wife Hannah Lawrence had nine children. Their eldest son, Jacob Schieffelin, Jr., was born in 1793. He studied medicine in New York City in 1813-14, and afterwards joined the New York State Infantry. He had risen to the rank of colonel when he left in 1825, to rejoin his brothers in H. H. Schieffelin & Co. He was stationed in Mexico for most of his service with the company. In 1827 Jacob, Jr. returned home, left the company, and turned his attention to his real estate holdings in Tioga and Lycoming counties, Pennsylvania. He moved to Willardsburg, later Tioga, Pennsylvania and acted as an agent for himself, his family, and others. Jacob, Jr. married Elizabeth Berard and they raised nine children.
In January 1849, Jacob, Jr. traveled to California with his sons Alfred and Edward Girard on the ship Morrison. They arrived in September, but booked passage home via Panama in November.
Richard Lawrence Schieffelin, born in 1801, was Jacob, Jr.'s brother. He built a legal and business career in New York City.
Clinton Emanuel Del Pela Schieffelin, born in 1823, was Jacob, Jr. and Elizabeth's oldest child. In 1844, he traveled in Wisconsin and Illinois, where he may have mined. He later tried his luck in the California gold mines. He moved on to Oregon in 1853, where he mined, farmed, and ran a tavern. Clinton eventually brought his family to Jackson County, Oregon and settled on a farm.
Edward Girard Schieffelin, born in 1836, was Jacob, Jr. and Elizabeth's seventh child. He served with the Pennsylvania Volunteers in the Civil War and settled in Wellsboro, Tioga County. Elizabeth Schieffelin, a sister born in 1829, never married and kept house for her father after her mother's death.
Clinton and Jane Schieffelin's second son, Edward L. Schieffelin, was born in 1847. He achieved fame as the founder of Tombstone, Arizona, located where he found silver in 1877 and thought he would be killed by hostile Indians. With the wealth from his silver mines, he settled in California. Edward L. (E. L.) Schieffelin later prospected in Alaska in the 1880s.
Mary Somerville Schieffelin Brady, born in 1895, was the daughter of Edward Girard Schieffelin and Mary Monroe Somerville. She gathered information on her famous cousin Edward L. Schieffelin and collected family papers, which she donated to the Beinecke Library.
SCHIEFFELIN FAMILY This family tree includes the nearest family members of those figures appearing in the collection. A complete family tree can be found in Box 9, folder 142.
Jacob Schieffelin (1757-1835) m. Hannah Lawrence (1758-1838)
Edward Lawrence Schieffelin (1781-1850) m. Susan Anna Stewart
Henry Hamilton Schieffelin (1783-1865) m. Maria Theresa Bradhurst (1786-1872)
Effingham Schieffelin (1785-1789)
Anna Maria Schieffelin (1788-1843) m. Benjamin Ferris (1771-1832)
Effingham Schieffelin (1791-1863) m. Mary Samler (1788-1870)
Jacob Schieffelin (1793-1880) m. Elizabeth Berard (d. 1881)
John Lawrence Schieffelin (1796-1866) m. Matilda Theresa Bowen
Cornelia Schieffelin (1798-1800)
Richard Lawrence Schieffelin (1801-1889) m. Margaret Helen McKay (1813-1892)
Jacob Schieffelin (1793-1880) m. Elizabeth Berard (d. 1881)
Clinton Emanuel Del Pela Schieffelin (1823-1884) m. Jane L. Walker (d. 1916)
two children died as infants
Edward L. Schieffelin (1847-1897) m. Mary E. Brown
Albert Eugene Schieffelin (1849-1885)
Jane Elizabeth Schieffelin (1851-1931)
Effingham L. Schieffelin (1857- ) m. Fanny
Charlotte Schieffelin (1859-1895) m. Edwin Dunham
Richard C. Schieffelin (1862-1919) m. Rose
Jacob Schieffelin (1865-1867)
Theodore Schieffelin (1867-1881)
Jay L. Schieffelin (1870-1934) m. Emma
Alfred Schieffelin (1827-1913) m. Kathryn Ferry
Elizabeth Schieffelin (1829-1901)
Laura Schieffelin (1831-1866) m. Orlando B. Lowell
Cornelia Schieffelin (1834-1910)
Jacob B. Schieffelin (1836-1836)
Edward Girard Schieffelin (1836-1922) m. Barbara Duttenaffer ( -1884) m 2. Elizabeth Schmitt m 3. Mary Monroe Somerville
Mary Somerville Schieffelin (1895- ) m. Hugh Picken Brady
Laura G. Schieffelin (1897- ) m. William Hale Wilbur
Elizabeth Schieffelin (1899- ) m. T. W. Durbin
Jacob Schieffelin (1838- ) m. Emily P. Ryan (1843- )
Hannah Lawrence Schieffelin (1840-1935) m. Le Roy Mason Lyon (1834-1908)
Scope and Contents
The Schieffelin Family Papers document the Jacob Schieffelin family of New York and Pennsylvania, mining in Oregon and California, the founding of Tombstone, Arizona, and a voyage to California in 1849. The collection spans the dates 1779 to 1992, but the bulk of the papers are from the nineteenth century.
The collection is arranged in four series representing four generations of Schieffelins and a fifth series contains the papers of family associates. The material in each series is arranged by the name of the collector or subject of the papers. Under each name, the documents are arranged alphabetically and chronologically, producing a similar organization for each individual. Series I contains the papers of Jacob Schieffelin and his wife Hannah. Series II documents the lives of their children Jacob, Jr. and Richard Lawrence Schieffelin, as well as the H. H. Schieffelin & Co., the family business. Series III contains the papers of Jacob, Jr.'s children: Clinton Emanuel Del Pela Schieffelin, Edward Girard Schieffelin, and Elizabeth Schieffelin. Series IV documents Tombstone, Arizona, through the papers of its founder Edward L. Schieffelin (Clinton's son). Series IV also contains the papers of Mary Schieffelin Brady (Edward's daughter), as well as material which can not be attributed to any one Schieffelin. Series V, Schieffelin Associates, consists of the papers of John W. Guernsey and Denison A. Lockwood. Oversize material has been placed at the end of the collection.
Series I, First Generation, begins with copies of a journal and letter written by Hannah Schieffelin in 1780 (Box 1, folder 1-2). The journal, written with aliases for herself and others, records events leading up to her marriage in August 1780. The letter, written to her father several months after her marriage, describes a trip from Quebec to Fort Niagara and the military officers she met. The rest of the series consists of the papers of her husband, Jacob Schieffelin. Deeds dated 1796 (Box 1, folder 3) record land transactions in Lycoming County, Pennsylvania. Agreements, deeds, and receipts for 1803-06 and 1808 also document Jacob's real estate interests as well as involvement with the Chenango Turnpike Road Company and the Susquehannah and Tioga Turnpike Road Company (folders 4-5). There is a photocopy of Jacob's journal covering 1777-96 when he was serving in the Revolutionary War and later in Canada. The journal contains brief notes on his life, such as his military appointments, births and deaths of his children, and civilian business transactions. The photocopy was sent to Mary Schieffelin Brady by Ken Moore, who wrote her husband in 1942 about Jacob. A copy of the letter is in the collection (Box 1, folder 7). The final document concerning Jacob Schieffelin is a death notice from a New York City newspaper (folder 8).
Series II, Second Generation, contains a few business papers of H. H. Schieffelin & Co. There is a file of accounts with Abriel y Canelas (Box 1, folders 9-10) relating to business in Mexico and several articles from the late 1800s sketching a history of the company (folder 11; Oversize, Box 8, folder 128). The papers of Jacob Schieffelin, Jr. make up the bulk of Series II. "Agreements, deeds, receipts, etc." (folders 12-29) documents Jacob Jr.'s business life. These files contain records of land transactions in Tioga and Lycoming Counties, as well as documents from 1813 establishing Jacob, Jr. in the drug business and records from 1813-14 of his medical studies. There are also receipts for sundry purchases and records of loans made by and to Jacob, Jr. His papers also contain correspondence covering the years 1811-77 (Boxes 2-4). The early correspondence is almost all from H. H. Schieffelin & Co. to Jacob, Jr. regarding business in Mexico, however, a long letter dated September 27, 1826, from his mother and brother Richard concerns family news and New York business gossip. There are a few letters from company agents in Mexico reporting to Jacob, Jr., and, occasionally, letters from Mexican colleagues written in Spanish.
From 1828 on, Jacob, Jr. was in Willardsburg (later Tioga), and letters from family, friends, and business colleagues document his life and business in Pennsylvania. The bulk of the letters are from his family, and in particular his parents, Hannah and Jacob Schieffelin; his brothers, Henry Hamilton, Edward Lawrence, Effingham, John Lawrence, and Richard Lawrence; and his nephew Samuel B. Schieffelin. Letters discuss family affairs, Jacob Jr.'s management of his and his family's holdings in Tioga and Lycoming lands, Jacob, Jr.'s business interests in New York City, which were being handled by his brothers, and general news of the city. Among the letters from his family are two from Jacob, Jr. In an 1829 letter he explains how road construction on undeveloped tracts is arranged, how much land he has sold and how much developed, as well as the financing of both operations. In 1829 and 1847 there are letters to Jacob from his wife, Elizabeth, who was visiting family in the east. Letters in 1848 and 1849 reveal Jacob, Jr.'s interest in California. A friend in San Diego describes the climate, political stability, and prospects of the area, while another acquaintance provides Jacob, Jr. with names of people to contact in California. An 1862 letter from his son Edward Girard discusses Edward's career and his regiment, the 45th Pennsylvania Volunteers which was stationed in South Carolina.
Jacob, Jr.'s military papers on microfilm (Box 4, folder 61) consist of his appointments from ensign to colonel in the New York Infantry. His survey book (folder 62-63) contains field notes of surveyors inspecting lots in Charleston, Tioga County, 1838-48. Further notes by Jacob, Jr. indicate he was somehow concerned in these property transfers. The book also contains several poems and records of Jacob, Jr.'s expenses.
Series II ends with an article from a New York newspaper mentioning Richard Lawrence Schieffelin as a wealthy businessman (folder 64).
Series III, Third Generation, contains the papers of three of Jacob and Elizabeth Schieffelin's children. The bulk of Clinton Emanuel Del Pela Schieffelin's papers document his overland journey to Oregon and his life there. An agreement dated 1845 records Clinton's purchase of land in Charleston, Pennsylvania (Box 4, folder 65). His correspondence, spanning 1844-60 (folders 66-75), begins with a letter from Walworth County, Wisconsin, where he expects to work in a saw mill. The letter mentions a visit to Galena, Illinois, suggests his interests in mining, and his inclination to travel. There are no further letters until 1852 when Clinton, now in New York, writes to his father about his California plans and his concern for his wife Jane. Most of his letters are to his parents and chronicle his voyage on the ship Pioneer and life in California. In 1853, he describes mining on Rush Creek, an eastern branch of the Feather River, and comments on the costs of claims and provisions. By August, however, he writes from the Rogue River in Oregon, where he and his brother-in-law, Joseph C. Walker, buy a farm and tavern near Jacksonville. He describes the surrounding countryside and its resources, including the mines. Letters in 1853 and 1854 discuss Indian affairs, and in 1855 and 1856 they report on hostilities. In 1855 Clinton writes that he is mining again and trying to sell the farm, but in the following year he writes of bringing his family west, which he accomplished in 1857. From 1858 on his letters focus on his farm and finances.
Among Clinton's papers are copies of an 1852 newspaper article describing contemporary Oregon and an 1884 article from a California newspaper reporting Clinton's sudden death. There is also a copy of an 1860 article from The Oregon Sentinel describing gold mining around Rogue River and an entire issue for October 15, 1864.
Edward Girard Schieffelin's papers consist of a variety of documents, beginning with an 1883 agreement transferring land in Tioga County to Edward (Box 5, folder 78). Canceled checks from 1888-89 place Edward in Wellsboro, Pennsylvania, also in Tioga County. The papers contain sporadic letters from friends and family. Two letters from army friends in 1863 mention Edward's plan to go West, describe life in the Army of the Potomac, and discuss black regiments (folder 81). In 1882 his nephew, Edward L. Schieffelin, writes to him with details of his three-year prospecting trip to Alaska. Other letters suggest that Edward was interested in an Arizona mining project. Letters dated 1887 and 1909 are from family and a business colleague. The rest of Edward's papers document his military career. An 1861 diary contains brief notes reflecting his personal and professional life (Box 5, folder 85). His military papers on microfilm (Box 4, folder 61) document his retirement from the state militia and his attempt to win the post of deputy provost marshall for Tioga County. Other military papers include receipts, letters to and from Edward, inventories, and other papers documenting his command of the 45th Regiment of Pennsylvania Militia in Tioga County and South Carolina, 1861-65 (Box 5, folders 86-90; Oversize, Box 9, folder 134).
Elizabeth Schieffelin's papers consist of two account books recording payment of household and farm expenses 1881-89 (Box 6, folder 92).
Series IV, Fourth Generation, contains the papers of Edward L. Schieffelin and Mary Schieffelin Brady, who were cousins. E. L. Schieffelin's papers document the founding of Tombstone, Arizona, and Mary S. Brady's papers contain twentieth-century materials on Tombstone.
E. L.'s papers begin with a copy of an 1878 agreement by which he, A. E. Schieffelin, and Richard Gird sold their mines in the Tombstone Mining District to C. W. Tozer for $90,000. E. L.'s trip to Alaska in 1882 is described by his brother in an article (Box 6, folder 94) and the prospectors are depicted in a reproduced photograph (folder 101). A biography of E. L. (folder 95) and his autobiographical account (folder 96) focus on the discovery of silver in Arizona and the founding of Tombstone. This subject is further documented in 1879 articles in The Mining Record (folder 97), Bullion Supplement (folder 103), and Oregon's The Democratic Times (Box 9, folder 135). Finally there is an 1879 report on the Tombstone Mill and Mining Co., set up by E. L. and his brothers to develop their silver mines (folder 100). There are postcards and other ephemera relating to E. L. and Tombstone (folders 99 and 102).
The focus of E. L. Schieffelin's papers is repeated in Mary Schieffelin Brady's papers. Mary Brady collected twentieth-century articles, tourist ephemera, and pamphlets on Tombstone and her famous cousin (Box 6, folders 104-09). She also gathered a little material on Oregon, E. L.'s home state (folder 110). Mary Brady's correspondence (folders 111-16) documents the formation of this collection, contacts with various historical societies and libraries, and her participation in the reopening of Schieffelin Hall in Tombstone, Arizona, in 1964.
Other Schieffelin Family Material, at the end of Series IV, contains items which cannot be attributed to any one Schieffelin. This section contains a set of genealogical charts of the Schieffelin family, extending before and after the generations represented in this collection (Box 9, folder 142).
Series V, Schieffelin Associates, consists of the papers of John W. Guernsey and Denison A. Lockwood. Guernsey brought and sold property in Tioga County which is documented in the deeds found in this collection (folders 120-22). His exact relationship to the Schieffelins is unclear, but he lent money and sold land to Jacob, Jr.'s son-in-law, Orlando B. Lowell. Lockwood, a friend from Tioga, sailed with Jacob, Jr. and his sons Edward Girard and Alfred to California in 1849. Lockwood's diaries describe the voyage of the ship Morrison from New York via Cape Horn to San Francisco, February to September 1849. Entries note the location of the ship, weather, speed and rigging, what they ate, what fish and fowl they saw, or which events they celebrated. Lockwood mentions Jacob, Jr., Alfred, and Edward several times. However, entries covering the journey back via Panama make no mention of the Schieffelins. The second diary contains a passenger list of the Morrison's voyage to California and a copy of an agreement between Lockwood and Alfred to be partners in California. At the end of the second diary, Lockwood signed himself "Engineer in Chief of the North Fork of the American River and E. D. James Quick Silver Machine and Log House." Several receipts, letters, and notes found in Lockwood's first diary give further information on the Schieffelins' California adventure (see Box 7, folder 124).
Oversize (Boxes 8-9) contains material from Series I-IV. The arrangement, based on the size of the material, parallels the order of the collection.
Gold mines and mining -- Alaska; Gold mines and mining -- California; Gold mines and mining -- Oregon; Pharmaceutical industry -- Mexico; Pharmaceutical industry -- New York (State); Real property -- Pennsylvania -- Lycoming County; Real property -- Pennsylvania -- Tioga County; Rogue River Indian War, 1855-1856; Silver mines and mining -- Arizona; Voyages to the Pacific coast; Jackson County (Or.); Lycoming County (Pa.); Oregon Territory -- History; Tioga County (Pa.); Agreements -- United States; Deeds -- United States; Diaries -- United States; Gold miners -- Alaska; Gold miners -- California; Gold miners -- Oregon; Real estate agents -- Pennsylvania; Silver miners -- Arizona; Soldiers -- Pennsylvania; Brady, Mary Schieffelin, 1895-; Guernsey, John W.; Lockwood, Denison A., 1811-; Schieffelin, Clinton Emanuel Del Pela, 1823-1884; Schieffelin, Edward Girard, 1836-1922; Schieffelin, Edward, 1847-1897; Schieffelin, Elizabeth, 1829-1901; Schieffelin, Hannah Lawrence, 1758-1838; Schieffelin, Jacob, 1757-1835; Schieffelin, Jacob, 1793-1880; Schieffelin, Richard Lawrence, 1801-1889; Schieffelin family; United States. Army. Infantry. Pennsylvania Regiment, 45th; H. H. Schieffelin & Co; Morrison (Ship); Pioneer (Ship); Tombstone Mill and Mining Company
- First Generation, 1796-1942; Series I
  Scope and Contents
  Series I contains papers regarding John Schieffelin and his wife, Hannah Lawrence. Under each name, the material is arranged alphabetically by folder title and then chronologically.
  - HANNAH LAWRENCE SCHIEFFELIN, 1758-1838
    - "A Journal During a Lady's Courtship," by Hannah Schieffelin, 1780 (typescript carbon), n.d. (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Letter to her father John Lawrence, 1780 Dec 4 (typescript), n.d. (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - JACOB SCHIEFFELIN, 1757-1835
    - Agreements, deeds, receipts, etc., 1796 (Box 1, Folder 3)
      Related Archival Materials note
      See also: Oversize, Box 8, folder 126
    - Agreements, deeds, receipts, etc., 1803-06 (Box 1, Folder 4)
      See also: Oversize, Box 8, folder 127
    - Agreements, deeds, receipts, etc., 1808 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Journal, 1777-1796 (photocopy from microfilm), n.d. (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Letter to Hugh Brady consisting of a biography of Jacob Schieffelin, 1942 Aug 8 (Box 1, Folder 7)
      For corroboration of the biography see Jacob Jr.'s correspondence, n.d.
    - Obituary, 1835 Apr 20 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Second Generation, 1779-1877; Series II
  Series II contains papers regarding the children of Jacob and Hannah Schieffelin and the company founded by Jacob Schieffelin, which employed Jacob Jr. Material is subdivided by names, which are arranged alphabetically. Within each subgroup, the material is arranged alphabetically by folder title, and then chronologically.
  - H. H. SCHIEFFELIN & CO.
    - Business papers, 1818-25 (Box 1, Folder 9-10)
    - Newspaper articles, 1865-79 (Box 1, Folder 11)
      See: Oversize, Box 8, folder 128
  - JACOB SCHIEFFELIN, JR. 1793-1880
    - Agreements, deeds, receipts, etc., 1813-19 (Box 1, Folder 12)
      See also: Oversize, Box 8, folder 129
    - Agreements, deeds, receipts, etc., 1823-29 (Box 1, Folder 13-15)
      See also: Oversize, Box 8, folder 130
    - Agreements, deeds, receipts, etc. (notebook), 1829-37 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - Agreements, deeds, receipts, etc., 1830-31 (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - Agreements, deeds, receipts, etc., 1833-38 (Box 1, Folder 18-20)
      See also: Oversize, Box 8, folder 131
    - Agreements, deeds, receipts, etc., 1841 (Box 1, Folder 21)
    - Agreements, deeds, receipts, etc., 1845-46 (Box 1, Folder 22)
    - Agreements, deeds, receipts, etc., 1849 (Box 1, Folder 23)
    - Agreements, deeds, receipts, etc., 1851-56 (Box 1, Folder 24)
      See also: Oversize, Box 8, folder 132
    - Agreements, deeds, receipts, etc., 1865-69 (Box 1, Folder 25)
    - Agreements, deeds, receipts, etc., 1871 (Box 2, Folder 26)
    - Agreements, deeds, receipts, etc., 1875-77 (Box 2, Folder 27)
    - Agreements, deeds, receipts, etc., n.d. (Box 2, Folder 28-29)
    - Correspondence, 1811 (Box 2, Folder 30)
    - Correspondence, 1817-20 (Box 2, Folder 31)
    - Correspondence, 1825 (Box 2, Folder 32)
    - Correspondence, 1826 (Box 2, Folder 33-35)
    - Correspondence, 1827 (Box 2, Folder 36)
    - Correspondence, 1828 (Box 2, Folder 37)
    - Correspondence, 1829 (Box 3, Folder 38)
    - Correspondence, 1830 (Box 3, Folder 39)
    - Correspondence, 1831 (Box 3, Folder 40)